

PHYSICS / ASTROPHYSICS PHD CANDIDATE | ANU

□ 0459 942 663 | Mansen.jonah833@gmail.com | Mansen.jonah83@gmail.com | Mansen.jonah83@gmail.c

| **②** JonahHansen | **™** jonahthansen | **™** @JonahTHansen

Summary_

Current PhD candidate in astronomical instrumentation at the Australian National University. Career aim is to work as a researcher in a field related to astronomy, satellites, astronomical instrumentation or aerospace engineering, utilising my critical thinking skills and technological proficiency. Full list of publications here: https://www.mso.anu.edu.au/~jhansen/#research.

Education_

Australian National University

Canberra, ACT

DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY Feb. 2020 - Exp Dec. 2023

• Recipient of an RTP and Dean's Merit HDR Supplimentary Scholarship in Science

Australian National University

Canberra, ACT

BACHELOR OF PHILOSOPHY - SCIENCE, HONOURS IN ASTRONOMY AND ASTROPHYSICS

Feb. 2016 - Dec. 2019

Recipient of a Tuckwell Scholarship.

• High Distinction Average and University Medal recipient

Loxton High School

Loxton SA

SOUTH AUSTRALIAN CERTIFICATE OF EDUCATION

Feb. 2010 - Nov. 2015

ATAR of 99.85

Work Experience

Australian National University

Canberra, ACT

RESEARCHER

Jul. 2016 - PRESENT

- PhD project centred on developing a beam combiner for the Pyxis interferometer (see https://www.mso.anu.edu.au/ pyxis/ for more information). Also interested in the properties of Mira variables using high angular resolution measurements.
- First year project with A/Prof. Michael Ireland in tracing back the positions of stars in order to determine cluster membership.
- Second year project with Dr. Brad Tucker in utilising citizen science to try and detect Planet Nine.
- Third year project with A/Prof. Tony Travouillon in designing and building an instrument designed to measure turbulence inside a telescope dome. Was installed onto the Anglo Australian Telescope in early 2019.
- Third year with Dr. Luca Casagrande in identifying relationships between stellar properties and the properties of the exoplanets
- · Honours project with A/Prof. Michael Ireland in simulating a linear formation flying, space interferometer mission with the aim of detecting biosignatures on exoplanets.

Mount Stromlo Observatory

Canberra, ACT

OUTREACH VOLUNTEER

April 2018 - PRESENT

• Assisted with the ANU Stargazing World Record Attempt.

Australian Astronomical Observatory

- Regularly give tours and present to school groups at Mt Stromlo Observatory.
- Given talks and written newspaper articles about astronomy (see http://www.mso.anu.edu.au/~jhansen/#outreach)

HEO Robotics Sydney, NSW PHD INTERN Oct. 2020 - Jan. 2021

• Researched and designed an optical payload for a future space situational awareness (SSA) satellite.

· Purchased and tested a potential optical system, both for optical quality and for survivability in space.

Sydney, NSW

Dec. 2017 - Feb. 2018

- Conducted a research project with Mr. Barnaby Norris in Adaptive Optics Instrumentation.
- · Designed and tested a photonic lantern based wavefront sensor, designed to increase the speed and accuracy at which atmospheric turbulence can be detected.

Australian National University

STUDENT AMBASSADOR Jan. 2017 - Jan 2020

- Lead tours of the ANU campus on a fortnightly basis.
- Team leader for major events, such as ANU Commencement Address and ANU Open Day.
- Gave presentations to prospective ANU students.

Max Planck Institute for Astronomy

STUDENT RESEARCHER

Jul. - Aug. 2015

• Conducted a research project into galaxy evolution and morphology with Dr Kai Noeske.

Defence Science and Technology Organisation

Adelaide, SA

Heidelberg, DE

Canberra, ACT

WORK EXPERIENCE STUDENT

Apr. 2013

• Worked on a tactical simulation between a submarine and an aerial assault.

Honours & Awards ___

AWARDS

2020	Peter McGregor Scholarship, Australian National University	Canberra, ACT
2019	University Medal, Australian National University	Canberra, ACT
2018	4th Place Presentation Prize, ANU Bachelor of Philosophy Symposium	Canberra, ACT
2016, 2017, 2019	Chancellor's Letter of Commendation, Australian National University	Canberra, ACT
2017, 2018	Brescia Award, Ursula Hall, Australian National University	Canberra, ACT
2015	Governor's Commendation Award for Outstanding Achievement, South Australian Certificate of Education Merit Ceremony	Adelaide, SA
2015	Chinner Memorial Prize, Loxton High School	Loxton, SA
2015	Gold Medallist, RACI Chemical Analysis Competition	Adelaide, SA
2015	Semi-Finalist, Rostrum Voice of Youth Public Speaking Competition	Adelaide, SA

OPPORTUNITIES

2015	Participant, International Summer Science School	Heidelberg, DE
2015	Participant, National Youth Science Forum	Canberra, ACT

Skills

Communication

- Given multiple public talks, both for astronomy outreach, as well as for communicating my research.
- Liaisoned with many academics for the ANU National Science Week research market day, achieving a turnout of over 50.
- · Written many essays, reports and articles for university newspapers and magazines, as well as The Canberra Times.
- Written technical reports and papers detailing my research.

Programming

- High proficiency in the Python and LaTeX programming languages.
- Moderate proficiency in C/C++, HTML.

Teamwork

- · Actively gained experience in leadership and teamwork through being a Prefect at Loxton High School.
- Volunteer and group leader for both the ANU National Science Week organisation team and the ConocoPhillips Science Experience.
- Lead a team of 10 student ambassadors for registration at the 2018 ANU Open Day.

Extracurricular Activities _____

ANU Physics Society

Australian National University

Jun. 2016 - Nov. 2019

MEMBER, SECRETARY IN 2017 & TREASURER IN 2018

- Helped re-affiliate the society after disaffiliation in 2015.
- · Led and organised multiple science based trivia nights.

ANU Music Society

Australian National University

PIANIST/TRUMPET PLAYER Feb. 2016 - PRESENT

• Played in bi-yearly concerts for both a general audience, as well as a pre-kindergarden concert.

ANU National Science Week Committee

Australian National University

ACADEMIC LIAISON Aug. 2018

- Organised and developed a research market day for undergraduates to learn what research is available at ANU.
- Main contact in finding over 50 academics and PhD students to present their research to students.

ConocoPhillips Science Experience

Australian National University

Student Volunteer Sept. 2016-2019

• Assisted Year 9 and 10 students by showing them around the ANU campus and encouraging an interest in science.